Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade (Completion 2018-2024)
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
In the year 1722, Emperor Kangxi of the Qing Dynasty
passed away, leaving 24 sons.
The Fourth Prince, Yin Zhen, was named heir
and became Emperor Yongzheng at the age of 45.
Two political allies, Generals Nian Gengyao, Governor of
Sichuan and Shaanxi, and Longkodo, Infantry Commander
fought for him against his brothers with
the "sweat and toil of warhorses."
The new emperor held the two generals in high esteem.
They were rewarded with unrivaled powers in the imperial court
and became the core of the new regime.
All kneel!
All bow!
Second bow!
Third bow!
All rise!
By the Grace of Heaven, His Majesty decrees:
(Su Peisheng)
Longkodo, a devoted servant to the prior emperor,
(Longkodo)
now stands as my loyal subject and the nation's meritorious official.
(Zhang Tingyu)
He is awarded the First-Order Noble Rank
and appointed as Minister of Personnel,
and Director of Ethnic and Territorial Affairs.
Nian Gengyao, Governor of Sichuan and Shaanxi，
is awarded the Second-Order Noble Rank.
(Nian Gengyao)
He shall oversee military deployments, funds and provisions,
(Zhen Yuandao)
as well as the appointment of frontier officials
(Gūwalgiya Emin)
and of the commanders and troops in Sichuan and Shaanxi.
This is His Majesty's decree.
I thank His Majesty for the heavenly grace.
His Majesty thinks very highly of General Nian.
Congratulations, General Longkodo!
We are grateful for your exceptional contribution to our country.
Great General Nian!
His Majesty looks upon you with great favor.
Sir, you certainly are His Majesty's right-hand man.
Great General Nian, could I have a moment?
Greetings, Great General Nian!
Mr. Su,
- you bring orders?
- I dare not.
The injury to your arm has been on His Majesty's mind.
I was instructed to provide you with this
specially-formulated ointment for the wound.
I humbly thank His Majesty for the heavenly grace.
May I ask how my sister is doing in the palace?
Consort Fleur has "the thousand demeanors of a phoenix."
Her favor is highest among all harem palaces.
Your mind can rest easy, Great General.
I'll be grateful for your attentiveness, Mr. Su.
My pleasure.
[sounding the night watches]
Hall of Mental Cultivation
[the emperor's residence]
Your Majesty, an official from Attendance Services is here.
Your Majesty, please select a name tag.
Your Majesty... You have not entered
the harem for half a month.
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager will blame me
if no name tag is flipped today.
Your Majesty!
Why are you talking so much today?
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager is here.
Show her in quickly.
(Empress Dowager)
Peace to Your Majesty.
Peace to Imperial Mother.
It's been hot. I asked the Imperial Kitchen to make
sweet mung bean soup with lily roots.
I quite like it.
I brought you some, knowing you must still be working.
Thank you, Imperial Mother.
Your Majesty, General Longkodo recently brought these pickles
for Her Majesty from Yangzhou City.
He said they are more refreshing than what we have here in Beijing.
Take this.
Don't be upset.
If every day is like this, we'll get used to it.
It's been over six months since His Majesty's coronation.
But you can count on your fingers
the times he's slept in the harem.
I understand Her Majesty would criticize you for negligence.
It must be hard now that you're displeasing both Their Majesties.
Thank you for your understanding, Mr. Su.
I'd be most grateful if you could frequently remind His Majesty
that the concubines miss him like the deserts miss the rain.
I would remind His Majesty, but he has been so busy
lately that he sleeps only four to six hours.
I've had no chance to mention this.
Imperial Mother, if you are bothered by the heat,
I will have ice retrieved and sent to your palace.
My aging body is not as sensitive to the heat.
Your health is what I'm worried about.
Working day and night -
your health has limits.
I understand.
You've been busy, but have you taken time
to ask about the Third Prince's schoolwork?
I did two days ago.
His calligraphy is coming along,
but he is making slow progress in the classics.
The prior emperor had twenty-four princes.
Your palace is not comparable to his.
I am not as blessed as Father. I only have three sons.
I shouldn't let this worry you, Imperial Mother.
There is no blame. He had more children
because he had more concubines.
Your harem is almost empty.
The Empress, Consort Honnête, and Consort Astuce -
they're not getting any younger,
and are unlikely to be expanding the family.
I do have the family's interest in mind.
It is the imperial family's priority to "spread branches and leaves"
so that the throne is passed through the generations.
That is why we have a Concubine Selection every three years.
This is a lesson for me, Imperial Mother.
So, we will have a Selection.
I accept your arrangements, Imperial Mother.
I am too old to arrange anything for you.
The Imperial Household Department
will set the dates for a few rounds of selection.
The outstanding ones will become your Consorts and Concubines.
I'll just be happily playing with my grandchildren,
enjoying their leftover candy.
Consort Fleur assists in palace affairs.
I'll let her take charge of the Selection
to ease the burden on the Empress.
Consort Fleur is pretty and proficient.
You have exclusively favored her all these years.
It will be good to have someone to balance her
rather than having "only one flourishing branch."
Yes.
But there's something I'd like to address.
What is it?
In my mind, one Selection is enough for me.
It is too costly to do it every three years.
Also, I believe Han people [the dominant ethnic group]
are family to us Manchus.
I'd like to select more concubines from the Han Banners.
These are less important matters. I don't mind.
I'm glad you're willing to have new concubines.
But do not make the old ones feel neglected.
You should visit the harem often
no matter how much work you have.
Especially the Empress, she is "the center of the harem" after all.
I'll remember that.
[Palace of Great Benevolence, the Empress’s palace]
Having asked you to come at this time,
I hope I didn't interrupt your afternoon rest.
Your Majesty has time to nap - I am less fortunate.
I wonder what urgent tasks Your Majesty has summoned me for.
It will soon be the final round of the Selection.
Have you made the preparations?
(Consort Fleur)
Your Majesty need not worry.
Huang Guiquan reported back after lunch.
His Majesty has ordered a simple selection due to fiscal deficits.
Although I have no tricks to make money appear,
I must not make His Majesty lose face.
How can an outsider understand the difficulty of my job?
I must thank you for your hard work.
I have ordered some new pastries to be made for you.
I hope you will like them.
Spring.
Please help yourself. Take anything you like.
You're probably tired of most pasties.
Autumn, bring forward the peony rolls.
Yes.
Songzhi.
I thank Your Majesty.
I beg Your Majesty's pardon!
I didn't mean to.
Have you forgotten the rules?
How can you ruin Her Majesty's kind offerings?
You must ask for Her Majesty's punishment.
I beg Your Majesty's forgiveness.
As my dowry maid, I expect more conscientiousness from you.
Unless a pardon is granted by Her Majesty,
I will show no mercy in punishment.
It's all right, Fleur.
Not worth getting angry over.
She is clumsy and dim-witted.
I'm thankful for Your Majesty's magnanimity.
I will make sure she is properly trained.
As the dowry maid, Songzhi has a different status than the other servants.
She shouldn't be tasked with serving tea and pastries.
Even if you are not satisfied with Songzhi,
there is no need to be mad.
Fuzi.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Peace to Your Highness.
Fuzi was recently sent to my palace by the Household Department.
She's a competent maid. I'll let you have her.
Although Songzhi is inept, my palace is well-staffed.
Your Majesty should keep Fuzi.
I always hear that your palace has the most skillful maids.
I hope new maids like Fuzi will have a
chance to learn from them.
She can do menial jobs for Songzhi
and learn to be better behaved.
I take my leave now.
Get yourself moving!
Yes.
I wonder how well the Selection is going.
It's due time for His Majesty to have new concubines
and expand the imperial family.
Stay away!
Do you deserve to be next to Her Highness?
Go! Stay in the back.
Dear Buddha, although I cannot establish myself like men,
I do not wish for a pitiful life.
If I will be married, I only wish for the best man in this world.
I hope we will grow old and gray together
like two interlaced trees.
I pray for the Buddha's blessing.
Please let my name tag be discarded
during the Concubine Selection.
(Zhen Huan)
This is a wish-fulfilling temple.
My Lady, your wish will definitely come true.
My Lady, every other girl wishes to be
selected while you want the opposite.
(Left: Vermillion; Right: Jade)
The Buddha will truly remember you.
Shh! A wish will not come true if you tell it.
(Wen Shichu)
Is it a special day today?
Is Dr. Wen here to make a wish too?
Dr. Wen has been acting strangely.
Imperial doctors can only visit
non-imperial officials with the Emperor's permission.
However, he's visited our household frequently.
Stop it, both of you!
I should ask Dr. Wen for a prescription
to treat your gossiping.
Shichu.
Huan.
I just visited your parents to take their pulses,
and your mother told me that you came to the temple.
I was taking a walk, to clear my mind.
Huan, you don't have to hide it from me.
I know you have been worried about the Final Selection lately.
I do what I can, and Buddha will take care of the rest.
Huan'er, my late father taught me to have a
"heart pure as ice; body noble as jade vessel."
He told me to give this heirloom teapot to my future ...
I have always held a pure heart for you.
If you accept it, you won't have to attend
the Final Selection.
Traditionally, under previous emperors,
girls eligible for the Selection cannot enter a marriage arrangement.
Shichu, I understand you're trying to help,
but your offering is too precious for me.
I cannot accept it.
Huan'er, I know I am just an undistinguished doctor.
But I promise to cherish and protect you all my life.
I will put you before everything else.
I have been satisfied just to see your smiling face
when I pay visits to your parents twice a month.
But unexpectedly...
you made the Final Selection, and I know that is not your desire.
Shichu, if you feel this way,
it doesn't do justice to the bond between us.
I don't have a brother, so I have always seen you as my elder brother.
And you've always treated me kindly,
like your own sister.
Naturally, when you get married,
you'll treat my sister-in-law even better.
I'm sorry for the sudden proposal.
But I sincerely wanted to spare you from the Selection.
Not only because of my feelings for you,
but also my gratitude to your father,
who saved my father's life.
- What are talking about?
- Our families have long been friends.
My father's past favor took no effort.
Think nothing of it.
My father was framed because of
rivalries in the harem.
He couldn't stay uninvolved.
If even an imperial doctor can fall victim
to the harem,
just imagine what befalls the concubines who are inside it.
I understand your concerns, Shichu.
But even if I avoid the Selection,
my younger sister Yurao will have to go next time.
My parents only have two daughters,
and I don't want to make the decision difficult for them.
- She's gorgeous!
- So beautiful!
(Shen Meizhuang)
Let me look at you. Walk around.
Excellent. My Lady walks with grace.
His Majesty will like it if she softens her waist.
Now, say a few words.
Shen Meizhuang bows before Your Majesties.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesties.
Good. Very well-mannered.
What if His Majesty asks about your education?
I have studied Poetry, Confucianism, and History.
Wrong.
Today, His Majesty is selecting concubines to fill his harem.
Not scholars in an imperial examination.
"Lack of talent is a virtue for a woman."
Yes, Mother. I understand.
You're here, Mr. Huang.
Gather up, everyone.
At Her Highness Consort Fleur's behest,
since we have only ten days before the Final Selection,
the selection hall must be presented in pristine condition.
It must be clean and bright in here.
If a single hair is out of place, you'll lose your entire head
for offending Her Highness.
Rest assured, Mr. Huang.
Now get back to work!
Yes.
Your Majesty should eat.
Just one more moment.
It's been over ten days since His Majesty came for dinner.
I heard Consort Fleur sent a servant to request His Majesty.
He is likely to dine with Consort Fleur tonight.
Your Majesty will feel hungry if you keep waiting.
Soon it will be the day for the Final Selection.
I am certain His Majesty will come tonight.
Your Majesty generously favors Nian Gengyao
and other high-achieving officials.
But for any official, achievements are easier to make than to keep.
Are you reminding me
to be cautious against his growing conceit over his achievements?
Only Your Majesty can be the judge.
Perhaps I am overthinking.
I shall take my leave.
Your Majesty, the tea is cold.
I will change it for you.
It's all right.
Zhou Ninghai from Consort Fleur's palace
is waiting for Your Majesty outside.
Her Highness wishes to have dinner
with Your Majesty at the Palace of Earthly Honor.
I don't desire to go.
Your Majesty prefers to ...
I will visit the Empress.
His Majesty departs for the Palace of Great Benevolence.
Your Highness, the dishes are cold.
Should I reheat them now?
Not until His Majesty arrives.
(Zhou Ninghai)
Your Highness, His Majesty is going to
eat at the Palace of Great Benevolence.
I see.
Please don't be upset, Your Highness.
Upset about what?
She's the Empress after all.
She deserves to have a meal with His Majesty.
But today isn't the 15th of the month.
Your cooking is getting even better.
I'm glad Your Majesty likes it.
You are the Empress now.
you should let the servants do the kitchen work.
I am your empress and your wife.
It is a pleasure to cook for my husband.
The soup is a fusion of flavors.
Autumn.
Your Majesty, our ancestors set a rule:
"A third helping is excessive."
Although the duck soup is delightful,
this would be the third bowl.
If you indulge in another ladle-full,
this dish won't be prepared again for weeks.
Fortunately, you reminded me.
Healthy eating requires balance and self-restraint.
That holds true for food, and also for people.
Is that what you wish to tell me?
Your Majesty is wise.
Your Majesty likes eggplant. Have some more.
The ancestors say: "Eat in silence; sleep in quietness."
Today's tea is delicious. Would Your Majesty like some?
No, I will go now to check on Consort Fleur.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Here.
You shouldn't be waiting outside.
It's getting cold in autumn.
I thank Your Majesty for the caring words.
I don't remember seeing you before.
Your Majesty, the Empress sent me to serve Her Highness.
She's pretty.
She belongs here in your palace.
How old are you?
I'm seventeen.
Seventeen.
Very young indeed.
I remember you were her age when you married me.
Your Majesty surely has a good memory.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Please form a queue according to your Banners.
Two in a row.
My Ladies, please allow me to remind you again:
You have gone through an extensive selection
and will be personally examined by the Emperor and the Empress Dowager.
This is a heavenly honor.
Don't feel nervous. All will be well if you follow the rules.
[Note: The novel's author is the woman in aqua blue]
Those who are not selected will receive a flower and return home.
If your name tag is retained, it means you are selected
to marry a member of the imperial clan.
The most fortunate ones will become His Majesty's new concubines.
New concubines will return home until your ranks are assigned,
and you move into the palace on an auspicious date.
The outcomes will depend on your fate and blessings.
- Hold on.
- Stop.
Keep going.
Go.
Stand in a queue. Two in a row.
Line up according to your banners.
Two in a row, please.
What happened, Miss?
You arrived behind schedule.
Greetings, Madam.
You almost missed the hour.
Had the gates closed, your year-long effort
would have been wasted.
(An Lingrong)
I live quite a distance away and could not call for a fast horse.
Madam, I hope you will pardon me for the delay.
Never mind, go in quickly.
Thanks to your blessings, Madam,
I haven't been denied entrance.
Others might not be as blessed as I am.
You have a sweet tongue.
Go in quickly. Follow them in the back of the line.
Thank you, Madam.
Go, hurry.
- Meizhuang!
- Huan'er!
I haven't had a chance to see you,
but I heard a while ago that you passed the previous rounds.
I wished for the opposite.
You had a long trip to Beijing. You must be exhausted.
I am well-rested after a few days in the capital.
I miss the time when you lived with your grandparents and we were neighbors.
We were just a wall apart and saw each other all the time.
I always remember the good times we spent together growing up.
Your attire today is plain and elegant.
Yet upon a closer look, anyone can see you're a canvas of beauty.
No, you are the most beautiful belle.
You dressed up so prettily.
Once His Majesty lays eyes on you, you will never leave his mind.
There are so many outstanding candidates today.
I might not be selected.
We must be careful about what we say.
Xia Ruhua, daughter of the Mayor of Jiaxing City -
Discard her name tag and bestow a flower.
Fu Hua, daughter of the Deputy Minister Fu An
of the Petition Department -
Discard her name tag and bestow a flower.
Cao Xiangyu, sister of the Deputy Minister Cao Biying
of the Ministry of Personnel -
Discard her name tag and bestow a flower.
Lin Qingyun, daughter of the Assistant General Lin Tingzheng
of the Infantry -
Discard her name tag and bestow a flower.
What is the matter with you?
You poured boiling tea on me!
You want to die?
This is the palace of the Son of Heaven.
How can someone be so impetuous and disrespectful?
I'm terribly sorry.
Answer me! What family are you from?
My... my name is An Lingrong.
My father... He is...
Can you not even say your father's position out loud?
He is the Assistant Magistrate of Songyang Village.
From some unknown, impoverished village -
Why send their disgrace to the palace?
Did you know you offended Miss Xia,
daughter of the Master of the Household Servants?
Miss Xia, due to feeling nervous over being in the palace,
I accidentally spilled tea on you.
It was not intentional.
I do beg your pardon for my carelessness.
His Majesty will not retain your name tag regardless.
So, what is there to be nervous about?
It is already your blessings from many lives
to have the privilege of entering the Forbidden City.
Don't you dare have any foolish wishes.
If you are upset,
I will compensate you for your dress.
Compensation?
Your dress looks newly made.
So coarsely stitched. It must have been rushed.
And the pattern went out of style in the capital a few years ago.
My dress is made of Suzhou Embroidery.
Are you compensating me with those plain silver hairpins on your head?
Or perhaps your tacky gold-plated bracelets
that no one would accept even as a gift?
Today's misfortune is entirely my fault.
I hope your anger can be calmed.
It's possible that we can let this go.
If you kneel down and ask for my forgiveness,
I will be magnanimous and forget about it.
Leave them be.
His Majesty will not select a girl of humble background.
Miss Xia is much more likely to be selected.
Kneel.
It's not worthwhile being angry over a dress.
Miss Xia, I trust you are a generous person.
Who are you?
My father is Zhen Yuandao, Deputy Minister of Judicial Review.
A deputy minister? Not a high-ranking position.
It's not about the rank.
It's about being reasonable.
Do you think you can command me
because you believe your pretty face will get you selected?
I dare not. I'm concerned for your good name.
We do not want to disturb His Majesty
on the selection day for the Han Banners.
We would not be able to bear the consequences
should His Majesty be troubled by this incident.
Besides, if others catch wind of this,
it may tarnish your good name and the reputation of our Han Banners.
This gain won't outweigh the eventual loss.
I hope you will reconsider.
I will remember you.
Everyone will remember you for your beautiful face.
Are you all right?
Thank you so much for your help.
I will never forget your benevolence.
Think nothing of it. It was no trouble at all.
Miss Xia doesn't have a friendly nature.
Do you worry that you have made her upset?
Let her worry about it. I won't.
It was very reckless of you to do that in the imperial palace.
This is...
This is Meizhuang.
Nice meeting you, Meizhuang.
No need for formalities.
No matter where you go,
"Respect is paid to a girl's silk dress before the girl herself."
Not everyone is able to appreciate
the elegant simplicity of the way you dress.
Since this is our first meeting,
I'd like you to have these earrings as a gift.
No... I can't...
Some day you will fulfill your wishes
and smooth your furrowed eyebrows.
Thank you for your generosity.
But I come from a humble birth.
I may not live up to your kind wishes.
Your origin doesn't define what you can become.
You are beautiful. Why abase yourself?
His Majesty summons An Lingrong, Yi Bingqing, Jiang Rulin,
- Dai Ying, Qi Siqin, and Liu Lianzi.
- Go quickly.
The six of you have an audience with His Majesty.
An Lingrong, age sixteen, the daughter of the
Assistant Magistrate of Songyang Village.
An Lingrong bows before Your Majesties.
Discard her name tag and bestow a flower.
I thank Your Majesties and bid Your Majesties farewell.
I wish Your Majesty eternal peace and happiness.
Everyone else looked displeased when their name tag was discarded.
But you expressed your gratitude.
I feel extremely blessed to have a chance
to meet Your Majesties in the palace.
I like the crabapple flower on your hair.
Imperial Mother,
let's not give her the flower since she already has one.
An Lingrong is selected. Bestow the sachet.
Father and mother...
I was selected!
I was selected in the end!
I did not let you down!
I made it!
They are just ordinary.
Nobody is perfect.
Your priority is children, not perfection.
That one.
Xia Dongchun, age eighteen, daughter of Xia Wei,
the Master of the Household Servants.
She has an interesting name [Summer Winter-Spring].
Keep her name tag.
I thank Your Majesty. I thank Your Majesty.
Xia Dongchun is selected. Bestow the sachet.
Shen Meizhuang, age seventeen, daughter of Shen Zishan,
the Commander of Jizhou Region.
Shen Meizhuang bows before Your Majesties.
I wish Your Majesties eternal happiness and longevity.
Are you educated?
I am not well-versed.
I've read Rules For Women and Advice For Women.
Good, they are both books about the virtues of women.
Have you read the Four Books of Confucianism?
Regretfully, I have not.
Girls are mostly taught the works of needles and threads.
It's excellent that you can read.
I thank Your Majesties for your praises.
Your name tag will be retained.
Shen Meizhuang is selected. Bestow the sachet.
Zhen Huan, age seventeen, daughter of Zhen Yuandao,
the Deputy Minister of Judicial Review.
Zhen Huan bows before Your Majesties.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesties.
Zhen Huan ...
Which of the characters for "Huan"?
As in “the slender beauties in King Chu's palace.”
It was a verse by Cai Shen.
Yes.
You are well-versed in poetry.
Zhen Yuandao taught his daughter well.
I wonder if you live up to this name.
Raise your head.
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.